You know, they say the hardest thing in
programming is to name your variables,
and they're not wrong. This video here
will technically not help you with that,
but it might help you to stay a little
bit more organized, write clearer code,
and understand what things like M
underscore mean and why they're used.
So, this is usually what people see and
freak out. This kind of
m_score prefix in front of variable
names, it's honestly not that scary. It
exists to add clarity to your code and
enables you to more deeply understand
what's going on just at a glance. And to
be honest, that's important. Now, we're
going to spend the rest of this video
talking about the how and the why in
much more depth, but let me just sort
you out real quick. M underscore is
typically used for private member
variables. So, like private variables in
a class, like here. S underscore usually
means static. Now, I use this for both
static class variables as well as
non-class variables with internal
linkage, such as this one here. G means
global and is used for global variables.
Those are the only three that I
personally use in C++, but there are
others such as C for constants. The
thing is, you can really just make up
any prefix that you want. It exists to
add a little bit more information and
context. I've seen some other ones out
there that actually refer to like the
kind of variable that it is. So like P
for parameter or A for argument. I kind
of made up this U prefix U underscore
for uniform variables in shading
languages. And I'm pretty sure I also
used to use v underscore for varying
back when that word was used more often.
And that's the thing, you can make up
any prefix that you like because the
whole purpose of this is just to add a
little bit more information, a little
bit more context to a variable. Now,
people also like to write these like in
a different code style as well. In my
code style, I write the letter first,
then an underscore, and then the
variable name beginning with a capital.
So, the rest of the variable is in
Pascal case. However, others like to
have the variable name in camel case or
snake case. And others don't even
include the underscore. They just have
like m and then the variable name in
Pascal case. Lots of different
variations all with the same point of
just adding a little bit more
information. So, the rest of this video
we're just going to talk about why this
is useful and why this is used, why I
personally like to use this keyword. I
personally, this video is just my
opinion. Learning programming is all
about practice. You can't just keep
learning theory without actually writing
code. And that's exactly why Bootdev,
the sponsor of this video, is such a
great place to learn programming.
Boot.dev is a website that takes
inspiration from modern game design to
try and teach programming in a much more
engaging and practical way. They're
basically trying to make this whole
difficult process of learning
programming super fun for you and kind
of communicate the sense of progress in
a really, really effective way. They've
got plenty of hands-on practical lessons
that balance theory really well with
actual practice. As you can see here,
you'll actually be writing code and
changing existing code, which as you can
imagine is such an effective way to
learn programming. As you go through
their courses, every step of the way,
you'll have to write actual code to
implement solutions to problems. And
they tie this in with gamelike systems
to make it so much more fun. So, you'll
earn XP, level up, complete quests, etc.
Their courses mostly focus on back-end
web development. So, they have like
Python, Go, JavaScript. But no matter
what kind of programming you're really
interested in, if you're just learning,
the language doesn't matter too much.
It's more about learning the concept of
programming in general and their
teaching style just does that so well.
They've also got this bear wizard AI
chatbot that you can use to help you
out. You can just ask it questions and
ask for deeper explanations along the
way and is specifically trained with
their course materials. Just be prepared
to feed him salmon. And check this out.
All of their content is actually free to
read and watch in guest mode. So, you
can always check it out completely for
free. You'll need a paid membership if
you actually want to access the
interactive features such as the
hands-on programming. There's loads more
to discover. Just head to boot.dev. Link
will be in the description below. And
you can also use code churno to get 25%
off your entire first year if you choose
the annual plan. Huge thank you to
bootdev for sponsoring this video. So to
illustrate this point of like you know
naming conventions and variable names in
general. I thought I would kind of
present this in like three different
levels of readability at least according
to me. So first of all, why do we even
name variables in the first place? Why
not just write code like this? Ah yes,
we have uh a new instance of a class
called a and then we call a function on
that a. We pass in a couple of ve 3es
and a float and we name that variable b.
Okay. Well, you know, let's take a look
at that function because that should be
easy to read, right? Okay. In this file,
we have a strct called a with a double a
ve 3. And then we have b which is a
derives from a. So, it's also got that
double a ve 3, but then it's also got
another ve 3. And then we have a class
called c. There's that function we were
talking about. It returns a B pointer.
So an instance of one of these. It's
also got a vector of A's. So of this I
guess called A. And then okay, what does
this function do? So checks to see if
we're within the size of double A, which
is actually up here. Okay, so that's
static vector B. So that's different
from this. And then we we do this and
then this A in place back. So I guess
that goes to here and pushes D back into
Anyway, I obviously know what this code
does. I'm just pretending I Let's just
skip past this. Now obviously this is a
simple example that I just wrote just
then. Even though this code is
obfiscated, this is usually something we
call obfiscated code. It's still not
that difficult to actually tell what's
going on. For those of you watching, if
you would like to hazard a guess as to
what this function is, what it maybe
should be called, and what it's actually
doing, drop a comment below. I think
this will be a fun exercise. However, I
I'm sure you can see that it's
needlessly difficult to tell what's
actually going on because none of these
actually have any kind of meaningful
name. It looks like it's just using a
random like letter or two from the
alphabet and it just makes this
ridiculously hard to actually
understand. Of course, you can still
understand what the code is doing. You
know, B time C and in place back. I
mean, that's not obiscated. So it's
still easy in a way to tell what the
code is doing but not the meaning behind
it. And that's the important thing. What
is the actual purpose of this code?
What's the implication of it? What is it
trying to do? That's where the English
language or whatever language I guess
you're using. That's where that comes in
rather than the actual programming
language. You know, I made a video a
while ago called like the most important
things of programming or something. But
anyway, in the thumbnail, I had number
one listed as CPU or, you know,
computer, device, whatever you're
programming. And then number two was
human. This is about the human part of
this because the computer does not care
what you call your variables obviously
at all. Does not matter to it. However,
to us, the developers, the programmers
actually writing this code, that makes a
huge difference obviously. And in turn,
since we are the ones writing the code,
at least for now, while AI hasn't taken
over, since it affects us and we're the
producers of this, then it can
negatively affect the quality of our
code, which in turn negatively affects
the CPU executing that code. So then
instead of writing code like this with
these rubbish variable names, wouldn't
it be better if it was this? All right,
check this out. Now we're talking. And
if we go back to the header file. Ah
okay. So A was entity, B was projectile,
we have game world fire projectile.
Suddenly instead of this nonsensical
code, we have this and it makes a lot
more sense. So this is kind of level one
in my little idea here. It's definitely
an absolutely massive difference to what
we had before. And it adds so much
clarity, so much readability that a lot
of people would probably just stop there
and be more than content. And this is
also how I used to write code for a long
time when I was programming in Java
before I really started using C++. I
basically didn't use any kind of like m
underscore or whatever naming
conventions. I just wrote code like
this. But to illustrate why this is
still kind of not as clear, not as
readable to me as it potentially could
be, let's just focus on this particular
function here. I'll drop it down a
little bit because usually you wouldn't
just have a single function in the file.
So this would effectively just be
somewhere in your source code. We have
this function over here. And if we look
at it at a glance, it kind of I mean to
me honestly right now it just looks like
it's got a couple inputs like it's got
origin, direction, and speed as an
input. It returns a projectile. So I
mean you know if I need to copy and
paste it into a completely different
class if I need to reuse this code
potentially in a different project. If I
just want to kind of look at it
functionally as just having some inputs
and having some outputs and some code
that processes the data. To me it kind
of looks like the data that it's
processing is basically all within this
function. And that's a problem because
if we have a look at this more closely.
Well, next projectile index. What is
that? That's not like one of the
parameters. It's probably like a member
variable. Oh, it's actually just a
static un 32t. That's all the way up
here. Okay. Then we create like the
projectile. We have this projectile pool
which again is not like in the class or
anything. It's just static up here. It's
effectively a kind of global variable
but just locked to this translation unit
to the CPP file. And then we have
entities which oh okay that's inside the
class. So as you can see it's kind of
difficult for me to tell all of the
different like branches like the strings
you know of like where does this connect
to? Where does the functionality of this
function like what is it reaching for?
What is it tied to? I guess you could
picture it as like coupling in a way.
What is it coupled to? It's very
difficult for me to see. And even
looking at this now, like I've just
shown you what it is. And I still like
need to keep reminding myself, okay,
these two are static, I think. Yes. And
then that's the member variable, and
then everything else must be a local
variable, either like a parameter or an
actual like variable that was created in
this scope. And you might think, well, I
don't care about that. And that's that's
okay. I once also didn't care about
that. But as you start being involved in
more complicated systems, like in my
personal, again, my opinion, this video,
in my personal day-to-day life, writing
game engines, it's really useful to just
be able to quickly tell what is local
and what is not. And if it's not local,
what kind of not local it is. So to give
you an example of why that might be
useful for something like this, other
than just if I want to reuse this code
in another project and I can't see what
it's tied to, suppose for example, these
projectiles were fired in like a
multi-threaded context. We might have a
whole job system that just fires
projectiles from various entities
because we might want to process our
entities in parallel. Maybe we even have
multiple game worlds. Like we could have
a game world per thread, like a thread
local game world. It's not immediately
clear that that wouldn't really work
because the projectile pool is actually
static. It's effectively global here.
And so we need to make sure that we
actually manage that multi-threaded
access to it and this next projectile
index variable as well. like we would
potentially make this atomic and then
maybe have this be maybe thread local if
we can afford that or we'd have to lock
access to it. I don't know that I have
to do that just by breezing over this
code. I would actually have to go in
look at these variables understand how
this works much more deeply before my
brain can kind of make those decisions.
It's also potentially worth noting that
if you're optimizing things like you
definitely want to know where that
memory is. I want to know if it's
static. I want to know if it's inside
like this class or is it local. That's
like really important to know. Now, I do
want to quickly point out that some
idees or some like syntax highlighters
probably depending on like your your
settings or whatever, they may actually
use a different color for certain
variables. So, they might use a
particular color for a local variable
versus maybe like a static or a global
variable or a class member variable.
Like I've just opened this in VS Code as
an example. And you can see that next
projectile index uh well actually no
next projectile index is white which
makes it seem like maybe it's not. I
mean yeah this is the syntax coloring
here is all over the place so never
mind. But in some circumstances yes your
IDE your tool chain once it probably
compiles everything it knows where
variables actually are. It can point out
what is like local and what is not
local. And of course that can be useful.
However it's not something that I seem
to have here in Visual Studio. I don't
really care about it obviously because I
use the naming conventions, but let's
just let's just go with it. In the past,
I remember having that feature. Maybe
that was like in Java or something. It
was never really obvious enough to me
just that the variable was a slightly
different color cuz it usually wouldn't
be a completely different color. But
then again, that kind of relies on your
like code environment, your IDE or
whatever actually like compiling the
code and making sense of it to highlight
that for you. which also means it it
wouldn't work in something like a git
diff viewer or like if I'm just using
fork and I want to quickly see like code
changes and stuff. All right, this
became a member or it became static. It
wasn't before. Obviously, whatever you
write in the actual variable name that's
more or less permanent. You can't like
get rid of that. It's actually in the
code itself. It's not relying on some
kind of external feature to go in and
like decorate things for you. So now
let's go from this to my version. So the
only thing that has changed here are
these two static variables and this m
entities variable.h I honestly this is
such a this is such a silly thing cuz
this is just s such a small function
like I don't know it's like it's like a
weight has been lifted off my shoulders
like I can actually understand a lot
more about what is going on here. Now,
of course, I'm used to this. Like, we
used to use this convention at EA, and I
obviously spent a lot of time reading
and writing code when I was a full-time
software engineer at EA. And it's also
the code convention that I of course
have adopted for like Hazel, and I just
use it in like all of my programming
basically. So, yes, there is that kind
of familiarity thing where it's familiar
to me. It might not be to you. So
therefore, it's probably not going to be
that dramatic. But hopefully you can
just see why I like using it and why
potentially you should try using it
because looking at this function now,
it's just way more clear. And if I drop
this down a little bit so that we don't
see the two static variables up here, I
know now that okay, this is actually
something that's like static. So the
projectile pool is actually external
first of all to this function, but also
it's external to the class. It's just
like a static kind of global internal
variable up here. And then m underscore
is the only thing that's actually tied
to this class. and then everything else
must be local. As you're scrolling
through code and you just notice things
like this, if I need to now take this
function somewhere else, then I know
that it's got basically like three
dependencies. It's dependent on this
projectile pool and its functionality as
well as obviously the entity where it
actually spawns that projectile. That's
now immediately clear to me without
having to dive in and actually start
inspecting the code. If I show you some
slightly more complicated code from
Hazel for example, like this like submit
physics debug mesh completely random
function that I found here inside the
scene renderer class. Same kind of
situation. I can look through this and I
know what is like a member variable over
here. I mean there's nothing static
inside here. There's nothing really
static in this entire class to be
honest. But as I'm going through this, I
can way more easily see and understand
like what the code is actually doing and
how it's put together. Not to mention
that I can also search for these things,
right? So m underscore and I can
immediately see like within a function.
Okay, these are all member variables.
There's also another advantage of not
just having like no space here like m
entities cuz then you can't really
search for that unless you have maybe
like a regular expression or something.
But m underscore will obviously light
that up. S will light that up since it
happens to be important to me in my line
of work where a variable actually is.
This is obviously a game changer. It
also by the way shows me exactly what is
supposed to be like an implementation
detail what is kind of internal and what
is not because I would only use these
for private variables effectively. So s
projectile pull is obviously something
that is static like to this class kind
of private here. G underscore is an
exception to that because if this was
global I would still have the g here but
I think it is important to just be aware
of global variables if you do use them.
But this m entities would not have this
convention if it was public because then
it's kind of like part of the API. You
can see here with entity position and
projectile velocity they're just public
variables that are part of this strct.
So in that case I just have them in
Pascal case which also makes the code I
think look a lot better. Like if I was
to actually access these variables.
Thank you for watching. I hope you
enjoyed this video. I hope this added a
little bit more clarity to what these
naming conventions actually are and why
they're used in the first place. Let me
know what you think of these in the
comment section below. Again, I really
like them. Personally, in all of my
experience, I think they help
tremendously. I will see you guys next
time. Goodbye.